foreign
[Music]
we're in active inference live stream
number 50.1 on October 20th 2022.
we're discussing the paper interception
as modeling allostasis as control
welcome to the active inference
Institute we're a participatory online
Institute that is communicating learning
and practicing applied active inference
this is a recorded in an archived live
stream so please provide feedback so we
can improve our work
all backgrounds and perspectives are
welcome and will be following video
etiquette for live streams
head over to
activeinference.org to learn more about
how to get involved with different
learning groups and projects like the
live streams and otherwise
we're here in live stream number 50.1
with our second discussion of the paper
interception as modeling allostasis as
control
previously we had number 50.0 where Dean
and I provided some background and
context and now we're really
appreciative that we'll have some
authors joining for the dot one and two
to unpack and explore some ideas
and uh today it'll be great to hear from
multiple authors see a little
presentation and dive into the middle of
things the thick of things as we do in
the dot one
and so we'll begin with introductions
then we will have a presentation and
then discussion so we'll begin with
introductions with non-authors first and
they can feel free to introduce say hi
and anything that they're excited to
explore today so I'm Daniel I'm a
researcher in California
and I'm looking forward to understanding
some of the formalisms in the model and
how they connect to active inference and
Bayesian mechanics and I'll pass to Dave
hi I'm Dave I'm
a um
discourse curator a student of Jacques
punks it and Mark soles I live in the
mile high academic city of Baguio 200
kilometers north of Manila Dean
thanks Dave I'm Dean I'm at Calgary
um
what's interesting to me is that
on a metaphorical level this started out
me in a in an open field and I got into
a forest and that Forest got denser and
dents and by the time we got to section
four of this paper I started reading it
over and over again which is a fantastic
sign because if I have to read something
many many times to really get my head
around it that
that's good because I don't question
things unless I don't get them that
doesn't mean that that it wasn't spelled
out correctly it just means that you got
my attention so
um I'm not sure which author to pass it
to First maybe Eli you'd like to
say hi
hello everyone
um I'm Eli I'm the first author on this
paper
so
um a bit before the live stream started
Jordan was mentioning that this work
comes out of what we were sort of
studying together in our lab at an
energetics working group
brain energetics reading group before
the pandemic really hit us
and so when I was
confined
you know I effectively started reading
and rereading you know everything that
we had gone through and trying to come
up with some way
to think about allostasis because
in our group and in our previous
Publications as a group The
interdisciplinary act affective science
lab we've referenced allostasis a lot
and every time I would ask you know how
can we give a mathematical or
computational characterization
of allostasis I would basically be told
well
you know we thought Peter Sterling had
one
and then I would go look at Peter
Sterling and
he's the originator of the concept of
allostasis by the way so there's
numerous works by him on the subject
probably the longest form
let's say
non-expert treatment would probably be
his book what is health
hey
and when I would look at
Sterling's work I would sort of spot a
contradiction or a contradiction in
terms
one of on one side
he's specifically charting the variation
in physiological parameters and
regulation
over time where time can be the course
of a lifetime in the course of
development or even just the course of a
single day
and yet on the other hand if you ask him
well how is this done he would
effectively
um say this is done by reinforcement
learning via the dopaminergic systems in
the brain
now the dopaminergic systems in the
brain don't track a shifting signal over
time they just maximize reward
and so actually in my view at least as a
computationalist they were more
homeostatic than allostatic
and from that contradiction and what
followed on from it really came
this whole paper
foreign
but to re-emphasize I would say and
before we jump into you know slides
material inside the paper
I think it's really worth emphasizing
just based on watching the 50.0 live
stream that
our group are more let's say biologists
and physiologists in orientation than
physicists
so Bayesian the paper on Bayesian
mechanics came out while we were writing
this
and I don't think we really managed to
integrate the two sets of material yet
together
or together yet
that's not to say they can't or
shouldn't be integrated it's to say
we don't actually have
so to speak we don't always have the
physics and dynamical systems expertise
of someone like Thomas Parr or Maxwell
ramstead let alone Karl Kristen on the
other hand
we have very concrete Notions of what
biology and Physiology we need to fit to
as really the bulk of this paper you
know the reason it's not just a short
section for with some math
is because we have to fit to the
physiology and Anatomy that we know
about
thank you Jordan feel free to intro and
then Eli off to you for some
presentation for sure so so I'm a
postdoc in the lab here so I think maybe
I'll just give some context of where
we're both working too and how we've got
here so
for me I've had a bit of a weird path to
get to this point in that I did my PHD
in social psychology and moral
psychology
um
it's then uh sort of trans got really
really interested in predictive
processing perspectives and active
inference and then really wanted to dig
into that and find someone who's working
on it around here in Boston uh so I'm
working with Lisa Feldman Barrett and
Karen quickly who co-direct the
interdisciplinary affective Sciences lab
here
um and like you guys saying the
perspective that we have is really more
of a biologically grounded one or more
of one that's based in um in physiology
and Neuroscience So Lisa and Carol joke
that Lisa sort of handles everything
from the neck up and Karen handles
everything from the neck down so
together they form a whole person
um
and what what I was really lucky to do
was I stumbled into
um
an existing collaboration that did going
on for about a decade here
um which we call the psychology
engineering Neuroscience group or the
pen group
where there's been an ongoing
collaboration with uh professors in the
electrical engineering department
probably most importantly Dana Brooks
has really helped to run it a lot that
Dennis abdogmas and Jennifer D have both
also been like really really involved in
this
um
and so what they would do is they'd meet
every week and they would sort of pull
through on active interest papers
processing papers uh information Theory
they'd sort of catch all of us
neuroscientists up to speed on
understanding engineering and we try to
bring them up to speed on on a sort of
biological understanding of Neuroscience
too so
what um
what we've been really interested in
doing is
thinking about some of the abstractions
that had come up in the act of inference
literature and thinking about how to
ground those biological processes
um and how to really make this tractable
at an empirical biological level and so
the interest that I've had in brain
energetics has been
um a way to apply some of that traction
onto um
my original interest which is sort of
moral and social norms so I've done a
bit of work on um
thinking about how we can think about
information or energetic costs of
information processing as a way of um
how individuals exercise control over a
social environment by conforming to
expectations within it
and then at the same time I've been
interested in going into the other end
and thinking about um some of the
details of brain metabolism and brain
glucose metabolism that are associated
with the Bold fmri signal so that we can
really Dig Down Deeper into the
metabolism that's underlying the neural
Imaging their image in literature
um but in the process of basically
performing this or forming this
energetics reading group where we've
been digging into all of those topics to
try to understand the brain biology
Eli and I really ended up working
together in this paper to try to apply
some of that energetics
um and biological work
um again with a ton of help from Karen
and Lisa who really know the details of
of the neuroscience and the actual
physiology I think Karen especially that
Eli would probably say has been like
really really really critical for for
understanding these physiological
systems
um
but basically yeah how we can
have some of the parameters and
assumptions of these active inference
models
grounded in real biological terms that
we can start to look to the empirical
literature the biological biological
literature and sort of gain some more
inspiration from that rather than just
living living entirely at an abstract
level
cool and with that I'll hand it over to
Eli
excellent all right
I've unshared feel free to go for it
thanks for that context
and just of note
um it did
um this paper does bring in some
topics that we haven't discussed on any
of the preceding 50 papers
uh many of which were also motivators of
what you
set out to explore so I'll just crop in
resize and so on and Eli please go for
it
all right
um
so before I really get into the material
of the paper I think it might be useful
to follow on from what Jordan said in
order to additionally motivate sort of
our turn towards biology and Physiology
here
which is that most of the time inactive
inference modeling
note that I say modeling or an active
interns physics so to speak
you need a term in your expected free
energy or in your joint density
that is sorry the generative joint
density not the recognition one which
you would call often I've heard it
called the prior preferences
essentially a probability density over
sensory outcomes that describes what
it's hard to avoid anthropomorphic
language here but oh well what you want
to observe
now in real biological systems that you
know as we sort of can hear from Peter
Sterling
or numerous other authors that cannot be
fixed
the that is you know prior preferences
can't be fixed it's I do I prefer
different observations when I'm about to
go to sleep versus when I am waking up
and the assumption that usually gets
baked into
principles like say the free energy
principle
is that
actually let me moderate that a little
bit based on conversations with some
free energy principle folks
if you have a non-path based a
state-based formulation of the free
energy principle then you will typically
assume something called ergoticity
and you'll note that we have an appendix
about ergoticity I saw that you
discussed it last week in the point zero
episode thank you for catching on to
that and thank you to anyone in the
audience and the listenership who caught
on to that
the ergodicity Assumption essentially
allows you to exchange uncertainty about
time or over time for uncertainty in the
moment
so you can just say there's a gaussian
prior preference density
it has this much Precision or this much
variance depending on which
uh which way you prefer to put your
division sign
and then
it's the same for all time
now if you're doing a paths-based
formulation
then
you lose the tie between the free energy
principle and
conventional physiological Notions of
homeostasis
because now after all can't the set
point be anything or everything
you need to know something about
physiology Anatomy to tie it back
and so that's really the motivation
we're coming from in this paper is what
if you have to acquire or learn prior
preferences throughout development
how little can you bake in
and so we start by sort of reviewing in
the paper and in these slides the sort
of perspectives that we study from study
the nervous system study the brain
one of them is predictive processing I
think that's probably going to be the
important one for this audience and in
predictive processing we talk about
the perceptual systems of the brain
really the sensory systems
as performing approximate Bayesian
inference
so then you'll have top-down prediction
signals bottom-up prediction error
signals
and there's this notion of active
inference
which says that we essentially treat
motor outputs
as parameters to the recognition model
in one of its in one of the earliest
formulations before there was any
expected free energy
But ultimately it still says in any new
or recent formulation we have some
notion of prediction error
between densities and this is an
information theoretic quantity
so really we're talking about a
Divergence or an entropy or a cross
entropy
we want to minimize that and we're not
only going to minimize that by changing
the top-down predictions that flow
through say the sensory cortex we're
also going to change these extra
parameters that correspond to motor
motor predictions motor commands motor
references depending on the terminology
you want to use to refer to them
so then in our lab where we are sort of
biologists of emotion
we often study interception
and that's really it's given a fairly
vague definition on the slide here
because there's a lot of debate among
neuroanatomists about sort of where
interception ends and x-star reception
begins which exact modalities should be
classified Which Way or Another
but really interception is still a
set of or category of sensory modalities
and when I say sensory modalities I am
mentioning that specifically because the
literature on interceptive active
inference
then tends to take what we might call
the earliest form of active inference
it takes the road of the earliest form
of active inference saying I have a
generative density I have a recognition
density
action becomes effectively a parameter
to fit the recognition density to the
generative density
and there isn't really a notion of
an internal generative model that
is separate that separates belief and
desire
so in a lot of the literature on
interceptive active inference
you'll find references to having very
precise priors
or even you know innate priors about
interceptive parameters
and you'll see this notion that
you use active inference in the
interceptive domain more than you use it
in the somatic domain
because you're trying to fit your
internal physiology to a notion of
apriori set points that are determined
by evolution
do you think you could give an example
of that Eli and what sort of set points
people might think
all right
let's see I've seen
carbon dioxide levels in the blood
mentioned glucose levels
um core body temperature is really the
one that I tend to go back to because it
really does remain constant most of the
time
it can vary but really that's an
inextremis type of situation
so if you think about core body
temperature
there's a circuit and I believe you know
Jordan correct me if I'm wrong but this
is the NTS again isn't it
the nucleus factors
yeah okay yeah
um essentially in the brain stem there's
a circuit that codes the
typical set point for core body
temperature
and from an active inference perspective
you could say that is a fixed likelihood
it can't be parameter re-parameterized
by some prediction flowing from higher
up
or rather most of the time it is not
re-parameterized
so that flows down as a prediction and
then every temperature sensor in the
body
can compare actual temperature to
desired temperature
calculate a Precision weighted
prediction error between them
send those errors back up
and then the brain can say aha I need to
find a way to minimize these errors
and doing so will effectively
keep you in an environment where you can
maintain your core body temperature
around
you know I think it's 98.6 Fahrenheit is
the stereotype
it varies for individuals
now the reason my next slide was about
allostasis
is because
while there are bubbly parameters like
core temperature
that usually behave according to a set
point
really physiologically most parameters
do not have a set point
they move the regulated levels move all
the time
so that includes heart rate
blood pressure blood sugar
blood oxygen levels
various hormone levels in the endocrine
systems
inflammation levels
shift over time
and I mentioned inflammation because
you know from the body's perspective
there is you know inflammation is not
something with a set point of zero
inflammation is sometimes appropriate
and actually if you want to think you
know what is the situation in which
adapting all of these core parameters
is physiologically adaptive
then
I think
heavy exercise and sickness
are probably the two largest examples
so for heavy exercise we could talk
about
say arousal levels
and that refers to the balance of
Cooperative activity in the branches of
the autonomic nervous system
but essentially if you're going to go
for a run
say from a predator or after some food
in your girl fashioned you know Evo
psych ancestral environment
you're going to need to decrease the
activity in some organ systems increase
the activity in other organ systems
and adjust physiological
parameters to be regulated to the new
levels
so this is a pretty well observed fact
of physiology
you know informally
Peter Sterling I would say having
invented allostasis as an observation
that gets made
he then
editorializes a little bit about it and
says it should replace
homeostasis as a mode of Regulation
so rather than having set points you
should be comparing to something like a
set trajectory
and in the ideal case when you're
theorizing you should assume that there
is no
Global set point of any parameter
and of course as we mentioned before in
extremists this is true if you get ill
your body does actually override that
circuit in the brain stem
to raise the core temperature that's why
you'll get chills you're at the same
temperature
but the regulated level has been shifted
up
there's there's also an interesting
point to make if you go back for one sec
you like to just that um in the way that
the sort of language of science evolves
here too and it's worth pointing out
because some people might be listening
and might be thinking
you know well homeostasis doesn't have
to include set points either you can
have sort of higher gold ocean uponio
stasis you can have um you know sort of
multiple levels of control involved in
that and some people have made the same
criticism of allostasis as an ocean so
there's a paper by Carpenter
by Carpenter that that does exactly this
right so
it's
but the problem is is that even if
that's like that's technically true and
people who really know what they're
doing and are using a concept of
homeostasis in that way might already
understand that you don't necessarily
need set points
but the the reality is is that the way
homeostasis tends to get used in the way
that it tends to be understood is it's
come to have some of this association
with set points or with a simple
thermostat model as opposed to something
broader that includes multiple levels of
control and so
some people who might be some people
might be curmudgeoni and want to say
that homeostasis already includes all of
these Notions so we should just reclaim
the term homeostasis for that
I think we're more of the perspective
that we're willing to just give that up
and it might be time to just start using
a different term to remind people of
those other associations so
we're we're seeding ground a little bit
when we're using the term allostasis
to just not have to fight with people
about what homeostasis really means
yes so Jordan is completely correct
there but I would actually even
recommend that you know everyone
listening if you can go find the paper
homeostasis a plea for a unified
approach by rhs Carpenter it's in our
citations and you should be able to type
the name into Google Scholar go look at
it
because it'll really explain where our
paper is coming from
as a short summary of what's relevant
what Carpenter says in his paper is that
back in the good old days they taught
control theory and controls engineering
to physiologists and that included
you know research physiologists and also
clinicians
and by back in the day he really means
back in like the 1940s to the 1960s
before another new approach took over
and she says hey if you're an educated
mathematically mature and fluent
controls engineer then you don't need
you know then these awkward names
are all really just different ways of
cutting the same cake
you know it's all a control system it's
a hierarchical control system this is
very evident he says in the anatomy and
physiology that you'll look at
he's even writing for a physiology
education Journal
and then he effectively starts
complaining that you know everyone's
sort of straw manned homeostasis down to
this thermostat model
and he has to complain like this in 2004
because indeed everyone really has sort
of associated the word homeostasis with
this thermostat model Global set points
things like body temperature rather than
blood glucose
and as a result
there's
as a result much of the actual control
theory got
simplified away
so even as someone who is housed in a
computer science department took a class
on reinforcement learning and can work
the equations of optimal control theory
I was not introduced to the concept of a
reference signal
as a Time varying function
until Carpenter
and that was actually pretty revelatory
for me that rather than having an error
function
who's
you know minimum whose Global minimum
is fixed for all time
you can have an error function that
measures the difference between your
actual trajectory
and a desired trajectory you can do
trajectory tracking control when you
have the mathematics
so we could say for our paper for our
purposes if homeostasis refers to this
thermiostat thermostat Style
Point tracking control
then allostasis refers to trajectory
tracking control
so moving on a little bit and getting
back on the main track
from our perspectives informed by
physiology and Anatomy
and a little bit of evodivo
interception and allostasis have Pro
have both
pretty well demonstrated themselves to
be
really Central to how the nervous system
is actually structured
and seemingly largely concerned with
the metabolism and deficient functioning
of the viscera
so for anyone who wants you know
citations for this I think it's
uh Jordan it would be Barrett and who
2015.
oh uh Barrett and Simmons 2015. yes
Neuroscience paper yeah nature reviews
Neuroscience
interceptive predictions in the brain
there's a more recent review written by
Karen Quigley our other senior author
on interception came out in 2021
and so you can really go check for
yourself and I would advise it just how
Central in terreception and visceral
regulation
are empirically to the nervous system
you could possibly design a nervous
system for a robot that worked
differently but the ones that evolved
are ubiquitously centered on keeping the
internal milia of the body efficient
so
um yes
um Dan tickles yeah do you mind if I
decided a quick question here of course
yeah because uh the the two authors here
maybe can just confirm that my parachute
is packed properly that's what I'm
basically wanting to
to be comfortable with so just stepping
back for a second
in that slide that you would just head
up there
the warp and the weft here the kind of
the weave that you guys were working on
on this paper was the allostasis and the
enteroception those were your focal
points right and then you've you've
spent quite a bit in sort of prepping us
for the difference between the discrete
time aspect of what you're looking at
and the global capture rate because you
say we can't we can't get fixed and just
the one saying I want to make sure my my
shoot is packed properly and then you're
talking about biology and physiology so
just on that on that great big am I
going to go Splat or am I going to be
able to land this relatively softly can
you can you maybe just
tell me whether or not that is in fact
is it a comparison is it an intersection
are these things running in parallel how
much of this is risk management versus
how much of this is strategic
I would think of it more as
an intersection okay and when we're
specifically referring to quantities
like the global capture rate
those are intended to be strategic
rather than risk management or epistemic
value
okay
so specifically there
there's a whole book on this let's say
it um Vigor the neuro economics of
movement control by Reza shadmir
and it Chronicles in very long form
extensively the empirical evidence
that
real organisms will time average their
reward rate
so in order to move from an episodic
setting to a continual
control set you know to a continual
lifelong setting
you need some notion of indefinite time
control
obviously you're not going to live until
T you know T reaches Infinity
but in the limit you do need to have a
coherent control problem
at least for modeling purposes because
you can't
fix the end of say a bird's life
in the lab on a laptop okay
and there's two ways conventionally to
do that one is this notion of
God and put the global capture rate
so the time average
the sum of all benefits minus the sum of
all costs divided by the total amount of
time
and the other is exponential discounting
now for engineering purposes
exponential discounting makes the math
and the computations much more tractable
and so in the early 2000s they
essentially found that the real you know
real brains
like basal ganglia you know and
dopaminergic firing
are best fitted by time averaging
and then on the computational side
everyone ignored that and did
exponential discounting
and so really when we talk about
something like a global capture rate
we're just saying we're going with the
biological evidence and writing down a
model that accounts best for the
empirical bindings
you know if you want to quote unquote
try this at home you are perfectly
welcome to go ahead and switch to
exponential discounting
it's fine or the machine Learning
Community is starting to come out with
papers on time averaging
you know lately the past couple of years
and that's one more quick question then
of course yeah thank you for that for
that explanation so if we're if we're
raising the the question around
tractability that assumes that there's
some sort of slipperiness or some
fluidity piece to this this thing that
we're looking at what what is that what
is that thing
that's fluid that's slippery that's
causing us to not normally be able to
model is that a feature or is that a
flaw
I would say the slipperiness is the
slippery that is the slip between map
and territory
okay
so when talking about real brains
we know that we observe time averaging
in the territory
what we don't know how to do is write an
algorithm
that provably produces correct time
averaging
and works in practice in engineering
okay
so let's even say rather than map and
territory because the scientist has a
map as well
let's say the slippage is between
empirical science and engineering
and when we write out our model we are
really trying to address the empirical
science and we don't mind if engineers
you know want to make their little
slippage and
use something that just makes the
algorithmics easier
that's fine
you know and in fact that is what the
Deep active inference Community does
okay so heading back a little more
towards active inference
when we read all of this stuff this is
sort of a bit of a Bible for our lab
Sterling and Laughlin
so Simon Laughlin was involved in some
of the earliest Publications on
predictive coding in the fly retina
Peter Sterling is the originator of the
concept of allostasis
and what we actually notice
as mentioned a bit earlier is this sort
of slippage another slippage or
contradiction
so they say when you get a reward some
dopamine is released
this invokes a reinforcement learning
principal algorithm
you know let's be careful with neural
circuits that we're not studying in
detail for the moment
that is Let's Be Careful how strong a
statement we make about their function
and then most of the empirical evidence
they review in the book is about the
Energy Efficiency of sensory firing
so we're really trying to say we want to
move from
something grounded in minimizing a
prediction error
variational inference
to something grounded
ideally with an optimality principle in
control
so then there are some arguments for
neuroscientists
which are more or less intended to
convince the Ewing neuroscientist that
people studying interception and people
studying motor neuroscience
need to work together on studying the
viscera
you can't study the viscera and ignore
the motor branch of the visceral nervous
system
and the functions of that motor branch
now regarding you know our statement of
you can't just minimize prediction error
one might ask what about active
inference
and
there we have to start being careful
with the term active inference
because you know as I have had it
personally explained to me at length
there are at least the two different
kinds of active inference
there's this very old
um I think it was Adams 2013.
you know motor active inference
predictions not commands active
inference in the motor
you know in the motor system
and then there's this notion of decision
active inference
where you have an expected free energy
explicit prior preferences and so on and
so on
and if you talk to the active inference
community
you know read the papers that they can
write for their own community
I would particularly recommend you know
the international workshop on active
inference which I believe is going to be
a conference next year
they have three years of very good
papers where many authors sketch out the
explicit connections between
active inference control as inference
optimal control
Etc
so really when we bang on saying you
know don't use active inference to
reduce motor function to sensory
function
we're talking to some psychologists and
philosophers
who have been
let's say quite enthusiastic about
predictive processing
but a bit eliminativist about some of
the mathematical constructs that are
actually used in active inference
so then for our psychologist audience
we have once again the argument that we
are basically
showing that you can and should do
a fully probabilistic notion of optimal
control
in order to sort out what is going on
with allostatic regulation
and we're going to take some inspiration
from motor neuroanatomy in doing it
so
looking at a simple model system
and this is getting into figures from
the paper
we have our Barrel reflex afferent
response curve
you have a carroted baroreceptor it's in
the Carotid artery in the neck
it measures blood pressure
projects to a circuit in the
uh NTS in the brain stem
and we bring this up here because the
barrel receptor is often used as a model
in terraceptor
when I talked to Karen and asked for
model systems of interception
she actually said you know well let's
think about the power receptor first
and again with contradiction
what we actually find looking at the
anatomy is that the baroreceptor the
Carotid Barrel receptor
is the sensory branch of a low-level
control circuit
so the NTS will then have
not I believe the middle inflection
point
is coded in the NTS here and doesn't
really change much but what does happen
is that you can get top down commands
flowing into the MTS
and then changing the gain of this
circuit
so the slope of the Curve
and if you widen that slope
so that the curve is shallower
than your preserving responsiveness
you're staying you're widening the
approximately linear portion of the
Curve
while allowing for the blood pressure to
rise and fall
and so again we see for the interception
people
that you really need to think about you
know what is the role of this
Interceptor in control
of the body and of the viscera
you can't just look at it and say it's a
sensor well okay it's a sensor where
does IT project to
um enteroceptive cortex no no not
necessarily like you know the error the
prediction error signals that reach
interceptive cortex
to say you know I can't pump enough
blood or something like that
might actually have already been
processed by
what I believe in the motor active
inference literature is called a reflex
arc
so there might already be a reflect a
reflex controller that has operated on
that signal by the time it reaches the
higher portions of the brain
so in our paper we set out some
vocabulary for people to use if they
want to
don't have to
capacity curve in particular we're going
to tie it to the notion of the
cumulative distribution function later
on
there's some physiology terminology for
people who want to learn it
and then we note the same thing that
Carpenter does
Carpenter and a number of other papers
which is that
this is a massively hierarchical control
system
lots of regulated substances let's say
or regulated variables are going to have
multiple controllers influencing them
so for instance
blood nutrient levels not just glucose
but I believe like salt
fat water
are regulated by pairs of hormones
sometimes there will be multiple pairs
of hormones per nutrient that has to be
in the blood
and this isn't a convex trade-off so
that's not antagonistic competitive
regulation
they can appear to compete sometimes
but actually it's Cooperative regulation
based on the fact that so to speak
chemical species can't encode negative
numbers
the way a digital signal can
so when you do things with chemical
signals having these pairs turns out to
be the way to
Monitor and control the dynamic range
with the greatest sensitivity
like
so then using this example of glucagon
and insulin
we can see that sort of normal glycemia
is really more of a range
and it's a range where you're going to
have approximately linear response of
insulin activity
and you're going to have saturated out
or really you're going to have
thresholded out
glucagon activity
so at a normal level of blood sugar
glucagon does not have to retrieve
additional blood sugar from the
intestines or the liver
it doesn't have to call for burning fat
Reserves
you essentially you've eaten enough for
the day you're fine
insulin is responsive in a highly
responsive mode where it can give a
linear response to a linear change
in order to compensate for noise
so now we can actually get towards you
know now that we have a controls way to
think about physiology
we can get more towards these Notions of
active inference
and here we're going to go back to some
of the sources
on that gave us motor active inference
one way to think about motor active
inference
is
the brain sense of prediction
the reflex arc in the spinal cord
attempts to minimize prediction error
by comparing the prediction with the
value read off of a proprioceptor
so again one way to think about that
is having a few extra ways to minimize
prediction error really entropy
another way to think about that
is to think of having a very Elementary
control system at the reflex arc level
and then the brain prescribes the
reference length that is the reference
signal for that controller
and it just tries to minimize the
difference between what it gets off a
proprioceptor what it reads the actual
muscle length and tension
and the reference signal
and this is actually a very I I'd almost
call it a fun circuit to study
because of just how well documented it
is
that there's something very much like
I would almost say like a Precision
weighted PID controller in there
you know if you're a math person then a
muscle is kind of like a spring
spring can be you know the Dynamics for
a spring
metal spring stretch it and crunch it
you know it can be linearized around
certain points
and you so you can just about write down
an LTI PID controller
for a must for an individual muscle
spindle
and you'll get two parameters coming
down from the brain one of which says
the reference length
and the other of which says you know
what's the sensitivity or gain against
perturbation that you should exercise
and this is actually how your voluntary
movements are engaged
so really
all of this stuff about references that
we're talking about here
is just putting forward to the
hypothesis
that maybe visceral motor control works
on the same computational and anatomical
principles
as voluntary somatomotor control
of course instead of the commands coming
down from say somatomotor cortex
they might be coming from ganglia in the
autonomic nervous system
with the higher level central nervous
system
basically just prescribing rough levels
of activity activation or deactivation
for the two different sides of the
autonomic nervous system
which then again in this opponent
fashion semi-opponent fully Cooperative
fashion
allow us to avoid encoding digital
negative numbers and thereby give you
very finely balanced control over the
internal milia
so we eventually get to our figure
which essentially says
if I know what resource supplies
metabolic resource supplies
nutrients oxygen carbon dioxide that
sort of thing
I'm going to have in the future
then my goal is going to be
let's not say to maximize uncertainty
nor to minimize uncertainty but really
to maximize resilience or freedom
stay in the linear portion of a
cumulative distribution function
where you can be responsive to any
remaining to any remaining or upcoming
perturbation
and so we draw here that you can have
this capacity estimator
close the loop
and start directing motor actions via
active inference
in order to follow this preference for
resilience against perturbation of the
internal milia
which is then tied to interceptive State
estimation
your other state estimators your actual
sensory service services
and this whole wiring diagram
and maybe one thing just to add too
right just to underscore a point is that
would I think if you go back one slide
here
and so how this relates to the
the sort of adaptive range of the
settling Point too and what I think is
really interesting about this right is
that
you're not defining
like when we started out talking about
how you might traditionally think about
set points for homeostasis in like a
very traditional thermostat model right
what you're talking about here is that
there's actually
[Music]
um
if the overall goal of the brain if the
brain is essentially there to help
regulate and adapt to sort of entire
biological system of the body to
circumstances outside of it that are
constantly going to be changing
different challenges that it's going to
have to be responsive to
then you don't necessarily have a set
point but you have a range
um where you can where
where the physiology can be most
adaptable to those perturbations and
challenges right
and so
even just I think to simplify a
sort of I think that that idea is really
at the core of what we're trying to talk
about radio like that you essentially
want to have um
arrange where the physiology can be
adaptive and yeah you would imagine that
if the physiology is if if some of these
parameters are pushed way way way far
outside of the center of that sigmoid
then you're going to have a problem in
that they will not be able to adapt
um to changes you're you're not going to
be able to be at that linear point of
Maximum adaptability if you're down here
near the threshold
and you get you know some random white
noise that pushes you over that
threshold
obviously there isn't a discrete
catastrophic failure
but also obviously you can no longer
mount a proportional response
yeah
your body is made of you know physical
instruments which have
a limited range of responsiveness
yeah and so our notion of allostasis is
to say
when you can
widen the range of responsiveness
rather than narrowing it
or rather widen the range of
responsiveness when possible while
narrowing the set of states or the
distribution of states that you actually
fall into yeah
yeah and so you look like doing somewhat
opposite things
and and so would it be the case too
right that you could have um
there's different ways that you can have
these systems become sort of maladaptive
if that if that's if that linear
if that sigmoid becomes steeper and
steeper and steeper where you basically
have it's just a very very narrow range
where you can actually have an Adaptive
response that can be one potential
problem another potential problem can be
when the sort of Baseline level like
you're saying is pushed far outside of
that threshold
then also you're going to require a lot
more work and a lot more controls or a
lot more control of that system needed
to really push it far outside of that
range to actually adapt to push it back
really to push it back again yeah
which could could cause other problems
Downstream as well right but but the
point is just that you um
the the sort of range that you want this
system to settle into is a range where
it can be adaptive to changes
and prepare for for fluctuating sorts of
circumstances right
yeah so
I think a good intuition to leave with
since we are get drawing towards the end
of the hour
is that
if you were to try to minimize
interceptive uncertainty
then what you might do is just stay home
all the time
your heart rate will never vary too much
up and down
and we're living in the modern world
where you don't have to run away from
Tigers so you know why deal with the
uncertainty of going out and exercising
or the perturbation of going out and
exercising
and what our notion of allostasis here
might tell you in reply
is to say
when you go out and exercise the curve
gets wider
and so the Adaptive range where you can
mount a proportional response
gets wider
so go out and exercise because it
actually increases your resilience to
physiology to Future physiological
challenge
so it's still within the active
inference set of intuitions but we're
really baking in this assumption that
you should preemptively prepare yourself
against possible challenge
rather than
effective rather than acting to avoid
possible challenge
we've moved the handling of challenge
into the body
uh Dean go ahead
as you get to those extremes of those
crisis moments we talk about a little
bit about this in the dot zero how does
the interplay or the instructional
proportion change
between something that's interactive and
and range seeking to
range re-entering I'm I'm curious if
that if the formalisms change as as
those extremes are are reached because
as you said things things don't always
become
catastrophic you're irreversibly
catastrophically
um
stat so what could you like based on
what you guys have obviously looked at
what what's your sense about how that
how that relationship between
interaction and instruction shifts as we
get to those really hard limits
uh Jordan you're often a little better
on physiology than me do you want to
take this or
oh no I'm not sure I think you might
have it
um
so
let's see
I'm honestly not so great of physiology
because I rely on Karen for it
I would almost say that there's a map
territory failure here
where we were trying to model so to
speak normal function
under
normal function with that intuition
about resilience against challenge okay
and there's several possible responses
to an extreme circumstance
you know one is that some high up
control mechanism
can start overriding these these
operating points
pushing them away from where they
normally are and then that allows you to
deal with
extreme circumstances by no longer
treating them as errors at all
so say if you're sick
your core body temperature is modulated
upwards that puts you in a fever state
this is expensive metabolically and it
feels bad compared to
how you normally function but it should
cook the germs
and then when the extreme State you know
when that emergency is over
supposedly hopefully usually you'll be
able to go back to normal function
there are of course exceptions such as
say long covet right
just just to make sure though do you see
a change in the amount of of literally
commands and the amount of back and
forth as as you approach those limits
do you think they kind of just realize
that they're they're getting closer and
closer to uh
a fall off point
I think that's actually an open and
empirical question okay so one of the
reasons that we like went as far as
writing a full mathematical model in
this paper
is because they're often
there isn't that much
empirical neurocomputational work on
interception at all so if you ask very
basic questions like
is interception predictably coded below
the neck
that's still an open question
it could be that peripheral and
pterosceptors are just transducing a
stimulus signal
and then it's only predictably encoded
when it hits the brain we don't know yet
so we'd rather have some
briefly lost Eli we've lost him but okay
while Eli's rejoining okay very
interesting
a different path
through the same material
Dave if your question is for Eli we can
wait a few seconds
not necessarily
um I have just a a a a side comment you
don't necessarily have to respond to
this the discussion reminds me of two
different fallacies one is the dark room
fallacy you know if you want to minimize
it's a kind of a parody of active
inference if you don't want to be if you
don't want to be surprised then just
stay in a dark room where nothing
changes which has been dismissed pretty
thoroughly by active insurance
activists right also there was a a
fallacy kind of a social darwiness
tinged
interpretation of the the observation
that every species has a fixed number of
heartbeats and therefore valuable people
members of parliament and clergyman
stood not work because you're eating up
your lifetime right which of course
doesn't isn't true because your heart
beats more slowly so it's stretched out
more if you're in good shape right um
but more more relevant
um the steepness of the reflex curve I I
sometimes feel that folks working in
active inference
cover may be too much with the notion of
precision that's this is one quantity
and it looks like the that slope in the
uh blood pressure curve but that might
is that something that would tend to be
covered by the term precision and if so
should that be a proportion a more
differentiated way rather than just
being a single number that applies in
lots and lots of areas of control and
perception
that's interesting so
so normally the Precision right is
normally applied to the predictions so
there's a there's an idea of
the Precision of the predictions being
applied and in this case I think
the idea is more of um
so it it comes back to where the uh
you might be talking about prior
preferences being targeted in active
inference models
um and I think the slope the the
response curve there is instead trying
to Target that use of Prior preferences
right so
it's trying to Target specifically where
is um
where is the system trying to be
navigated it's it's been
yeah when people talk about prior
preferences they've talked about it
sometimes in terms of uh
the system having a sort of strong prior
strong precise priors being encoded
um
like a priori prior is being encoded uh
to be targeted
and in this case I think it's um
we're trying to give an account of where
some of those priors can come from and
how these systems and how sort of
opponent processes
can or opponent uh chemicals can help
regulate the physiology
um
and we're trying to get a more natural
approach of where those can come about
from so
but
I think um
if it is replaced I'm just trying to
think to talk aloud to Think Through the
question so
if it is replacing basically a prior
preference
and um
if normally that prior preference would
be handled by uh
a sort of precision account of it
then to some extent the um
the steepness of that curve is trying to
tackle uh it's somewhat of a replacement
of the Precision but
um
but yeah it's uh
it's it's giving a different
way of um
yeah maybe it is a replacement for the
position in that case
Eli's back so maybe you I can try to
answer your question Eli do you want to
complete your presentation
um sure but if just to answer the
question if we're talking about the gain
on one of these signoid curves
then
yeah that's sort of a replacement for
the Precision but it's really thinking
about
it's thinking about it the all the other
way around
so a variance quantifies your tolerance
for error
a Precision or a gain quantifies
response to error
yes
yeah so when you're talking about purely
sensory
these extra receptive signals
the ones that aren't prescribing
references to you in any way
then of course you know you want to save
the neural response which is
metabolically expensive
for precise signals
if you're talking about an internal
you know physiological curve
say reaction to a change in blood
pressure
then you want to try and
make the gain shallower you want to
tolerate variance
sorry about
um getting
my
my home modem I think just restarted
itself for no apparent reason we call
that a sleep wake cycle
yeah
um how about it did some sleep phase
gradient updates
but it's simpler it's refreshed
um it's ready for you to complete the
presentation and then we'll
return very um interesting though
so
okay
um
see share screen here we are all right
continue
yeah so now we start getting into
really what scant
um visual material is available for
section four
which I think we'll have to go over in
detail in a more q a format a little bit
but
so if we then want to talk about how do
we integrate decision active inference
into this allostatic View
then we can say decision making is this
notion of optimal control control
subject to a set of expectations about
the future
so we'll have to write an objective
function
and then we'll have our wiring diagram
back
and we'll note that motor references
issued top down
are now conditioned upon or subject to
predictions about the future
then part of how we're going to get into
what this objective function is actually
made up out of
is to First Take the intuition
that if we start from neural circuits
that can only do predictive processing
as we know it
then one thing we can do with them
is you know simulate some Ensemble or
population
of potential
state trajectories or really State
action trajectories
starting from some initial state
then you know given an objective
function
we can estimate the time average
given our ensemble
we can turn that into feedback control
getting the stability in control theory
the closed loop stability derived from
using feedback
by then having a recognition model
and then we can say ah
I'm going to update my entire ensemble
or population
of simulations
by taking them from the recognition
model
which is conditional upon observed
sensory outcomes
and then having predictions from the
recognition density
which we're superscripting here with
superscript you know parentheses too
in comparison to superscript parentheses
one here
we can then penalize a notion of
distance
so really we can penalize the
quote-unquote size of the update
in information theoretic terms
and if you've seen a free energy or an
expected free energy written out term by
term before
you should have seen one of these it's a
KL Divergence
but what that gives us is feedback
stabilized control
using probability models
and that actually gets to more or less
the end of the slides per se
so as a few summary points
are computational model
gives us a useful notion of affordance
competition
basically run up run a bunch of forward
simulations
pick the ones that are going to have
good expected values over time averaging
to actually enact
as motor references
the
sigmoidal curves
after we've taken their derivatives to
convert them to probability densities
you know then taking the logarithm of
those to convert to log densities
which is much more typical for you know
active inference like a log prior
preference
those actually provide a notion of
common currency
foreign because now we've normalized you
know all notion of probability Mass to
one
so a density over one variable and a
density over the other variable have the
same units
we don't need any more notion of a
reward currency in this model
then there's some encouragement
for the anatomists and physiologists to
say hey
let's go look at autonomic and visceral
motor regulation
and see if we can understand it
in terms of these motor control circuits
at the low level
and that just brings us to you know some
very overall conclusions
ideally our work should be placed in
dialogue with you know active inference
as control work by other authors
and of course acknowledgments you can
really see here how much work went into
this on behalf of absolutely everyone in
the team
and references
so I'll stop sharing and we can shift to
a more interactive format
awesome
well thanks for
sharing that and so where was that
previously shared in what context
um just in the context of our lab group
all right cool
so we're going to slide the College of
Engineering Group we were talking yeah
yeah so the slides are really made for
this like
biologists psychology with a few
engineers group
cool
okay well many
many ways many paths to go
just to kind of highlight a few pieces
under this
broad umbrella of physiology one
important point you raised
um was how much
homeostasis
same
stasis
is in effect versus a mechanism of
actually is that stabilization sometimes
empirically of stasis
and even homeostasis
is that under Lane by a drive to a set
point as it has been simplified or
understood as in that simple thermometer
model and then to what extent do we
bring in allostasis hormesis arousal
and different physiological phenomena
and consider these all part of just the
dynamic and multimodal homeostatic
engagements of complex bodies
versus
um
discard the old and with the new and how
much to lump and split physiology when
even at the single cellular life form
level
they're engaging
from a computational or control or
information theoretic perspective in
processes that are analogous to some of
these
that's one point that we can explore
another area to explore is
on that theme of what are these systems
doing
and how do we model it the map territory
or the
um engineering basic research question
we could talk about a given
physiological process body temperature
stabilization or the baroreceptor the
glucose and so on
is there the minimization of a
difference
for example between preferred and
observed
is there a maximization of reward
According to some reward function
is there a maximization of precision
Precision on what
is there a maximization of responsivity
which corresponds in the sigmoidal curve
family to the linearized region
are there cases where all four of these
things are going to be happening
indistinguishably
is there a case where some of these
phenomena are occurring at the detriment
of others
can we differentiate models and actually
make unique predictions explanations and
control systems
if we move our emphasis from one of
these lenses to another lens
and how should we think about different
physiological systems ranging from the
implicit and very
ancient mechanisms
to those which consciously may even feel
like for example error minimization
reward maximization precision
maximization responsivity maximization
so I'll
pause there and either authors may make
some remarks or anyone May raise a
question or thought
Eli I just wanted to ask you maybe just
to direct within this because you talked
at the end about a
that this gets us away from
having to have a reward currency
oh yeah and maybe I'd be interested if
you can elaborate on that a little bit
so
just um what would the typical role of a
reward currency would be and how does
this sort of how does the the framework
that you're proposing change that right
yeah so really I'd back off and say you
know what changes this is the active
inference point of view right so quote
unquote typically if you're doing
something like
um if you're someone like Yale Neve or
Sam gershman then you think about reward
as in a reinforcement learning terms as
something that the brain has to maximize
and then you would say all right well I
want
the uncertainty of my beliefs to be
minimized while I maximize reward
so those are then two separate modular
computations that have almost opposite
goals one of them is to minimize
uncertainty right now and the other is
to maximize reward over the long term
and incomes you know active inference
and really says no no if you phrase this
as a variational optimization problem
then you can get a unified objective for
this
where you know the common currency is so
to speak
um evidence
really you know evidence that you're
following the correct trajectory
evidence that you're executing a
behavior correct trade
and evidence series you know in terms of
I guess we would call them gnats or bits
are the units and information Theory so
if you're using
you know e as the basis of your
logarithm
then it's not if you're using a log 2
base it's bits
my dogs are getting picked up for their
walks so
yes this is a very interesting
complementary perspective
where we'll get reward maximization over
time
when we
increase our Precision now everybody
agrees on that and is it going to be the
cart before the horse or the horse
before the car and which one's the horse
and which one's the cart
and framing the unified objective
function in information theoretic terms
as a surprisal bounding heuristic as has
been done in Bayesian evidence lower
bounds for a long time by Framing
surprise minimization bounding as the
unified objective function and currency
then there is the realized
maintenance of homeostasis or however we
want to call that
without needing a traditionally
structured
maximization of reward as defined by a
reward or time discounted reward
function
and it's also very uh interesting like
we're not trying to accumulate body
temperature we're not trying to
accumulate glucose
if we were playing a game where simply
more points were better
like some social and sub-social games
then a unilateral optimization via
maximization Paradigm makes a lot of
sense
but for the kind of physiological
infinite games that we play
as you highlighted with the infinite
Horizon
then it may make more sense
to have a bounded responsibility
and an emphasis on controllability
under inherited priors that those
controllable ranges are the survivable
ranges otherwise how could one have
existed for Generations
rather than try to
Stack Up glucose
yeah so I think
it's always really interesting to go
back and read Peter Sterling in this
light
because
you know beyond just the formal
physiological material
there are these stories that he can tell
of for instance people living in
long-term stressful situations
and they develop what we would Now call
the diseases of civilization
which you know you Sterling sort of
implies are the diseases of homeostasis
living too much the same too much of the
time
and indeed speaking of you know not
wanting to stack up glucose
this is that you know this is an actual
disease that happens to people that is
called diabetes
it is considered a pathology and so
there's
almost an interesting you know Misfit
between that intuitive notion of reward
or at least
let's sneer slightly and say that
economic notion of reward
which has to be a form of accumulative
wealth in a common currency
versus physiology in which too much of a
good thing is actually a bad thing again
right and and that actually comes back
to if you there's a part of what this is
contributing then right in one ways is a
sort of shift in metaphor right or it's
I think that point about a
an economic conception and value and of
reward
is
it's useful to have a Counterpoint to
that because as Eli is saying
there is no upper limit to economic
reward there's a benefit to accumulating
it you think about sort of accumulating
Capital to spend it
um
in this case right what what we're
focusing on is
how to
basically keep balanced and adaptable
so that future challenges can be
actually encountered and dealt with and
that sometimes means packing light not
keeping so much glucose on hand so that
you can very like deal with the reward
or deal with changing circumstances and
adapt to them
but you can't um
it's actually it's maybe yeah it's it's
maybe been a pretty serious problem to
have this
completely abstracted notion of value
that
um
is endlessly accumulatable and doesn't
actually
doesn't interface with any of the
biological realities of um
of what systems are actually doing right
there's yeah it's it's it's so it's so
abstract that it's um
it's it's gonna have a really hard time
interfacing with Biology
yeah before we go to the question let's
say let's sum that up by saying bank
accounts are unbounded and they're
useful because they're unbounded
you know the account like an economist
can conceive of trillions of dollars in
assets
in a way that my body cannot
bodies are bounded
if you you know they are physically
bounded they are made of a finite amount
of matter at once
if you try to put too much more into
them something bad will happen
naturally after setting this up on that
channel discussion I've got to duck off
a little bit early but I'm going to try
to be back for 50.2 next week and I'm
really interested to see where this
conversation goes so I'll catch up on
the hubs thank you
um all right thanks
if nobody Minds I'd like to ask Dave his
question first just because I was about
to when I got kicked off
yep go for it Dave
or um is that one that I said
um yeah I know which one that was
um if you have a new question it's fine
I oh yeah that's probably better um
her two
pieces of civilization there is the
rumor and maybe this was just a fallacy
or a misunderstanding that people who
managed to stay in London during the
blitz under conditions that you would
expect would produce massive amount of
psycho
um psychosomatic disease hysteria
conversion syndromes that it didn't
happen people were just preposterously
sane because they didn't have time to be
sick they didn't have time to be crazy
did that really happen
did the sense of mission override what
otherwise would have been General stress
syndrome causing breakdowns
um does someone know the detailed
history of the London Blitz in World War
II because I really don't it's a great
uh not English dot 1.5
um Journey for us to explore but to to
speak to it generally
it's an interesting question as well to
what extent by comforting and
regularizing
we even work against that and let alone
neglect other trade-offs and incur
externalities
um Dean
Eli this has been fantastic I so here's
here's my thing
um and I maybe in the in the in the dot
two we'll we'll get into the I I
mentioned at the end of the dot zero I
was I was hoping you really had some
really velvet gloves to walk me through
the 4.4 because
and especially after the context you've
been able to provide us today around the
idea that
[Music]
um
you know engineers and psychologists
came into a room now I don't know if
that once you got into that room it
became an intersection with red light
green light and you guys kind of played
a Red Rover come on over thing or
weather and you know it so well well
here's the thing because I actually did
work with CFOs and engineers and and so
what you discover is there's a bit of an
isomorphist I want to be able to diagram
this out for you view that that tends to
be biased for engineers and then there's
the spatially enveloped view of the
psychologist right like they're in their
phenomenological space and what you've
done
is you've tried to say what what when
those two worlds come together I don't
know if it's a collision I don't know if
it's a cooperation it's a variety of
things right it's complicated we'll just
leave it there but my my question is
this as I got to 4.4 it felt like if I
was skiing I went from a beautiful
powder field to some sparsely
um distance trees to Tighter and Tighter
and finally I was like I don't know how
I can keep going because there doesn't
seem to be any more gaps here it's just
getting too tight for me and the
reconciliation like when you're skiing
as a metaphor is you're not looking at
the trees
you're looking at the at the non thing
it's the non-objects it's a
Reconciliation
and when we're talking about dodgeball
as your metaphor or whether we're
talking about
glucagon control these to me what you
were describing up until that point was
essentially you were saying for us to
know what's going on we're going to look
at the risk management we're going to
look at the coordination we're going to
look at those things that are
essentially backwards facing we can say
that in order for the process to carry
forward continue there has to be some
addressing of those factors and then
there has to be the reconciliation just
like when the engineers and the
psychologists are proximal to one
another it's an entanglement and and
it's not a the engineers get to tell the
psychologists what to do any more than
the psychologists get to tell the
engineers what to do right so
if
if the behavioral piece if the idea of
the biology and the physiology is if I
do this now in real terms
I have to look at that and you guys had
an L4 different time frames
right I can manage that you spoke
clearly to that I I I read that and it
was clear to me I was I I got it I can
coordinate that
and again that was very very clear and
then
I got to 4.4
and I simply lost the thread because
what I was looking for was the
reconciliation I will align this next
move with the range recapitulator that's
what I was expecting next and then so I
went okay so where is the strategy
because that's there when when
psychologists and engineers get into a
room they don't just abandon their
strategy it comes with them it follows
them into that space and carries them to
that question of I reconcile
an advantage and all of the above until
I choose this Choice while always
keeping all the above so you guys talked
about that in other parts of it you said
we can't just abandon it
but I couldn't understand how the
formalism
reconciled it
so I'm sorry that's such a long-winded
question but picture paper oh it's
awesome to spend six hours of my life
going these guys have got to be much
closer to answering this because I've
never been able to answer it but then I
got lost and I just felt like oh man
what am I missing
okay so
I'm gonna disappoint you slightly and
say you know what you're missing is that
I think what's missing from our writing
is really being clear that we're working
under a very unusual
set of constraints in how we formulated
this model
so specifically unlike say
Sam gershman Oriel leave
or unlike the literature on deep active
inference in computers
we're assuming that you essentially
don't need
an extra set of computational
ingredients for reinforcement learning
so we're saying assuming that you can do
only the
computational operations known to be
involved in predictive processing
what can you come up with that will
handle a control problem
and the answer is this very specific
thing with these nastily involved
derivations
called path integral control
and you'll notice that when I was going
over those slides I basically said let's
just say you can simulate
you know possible futures
like Possible episode length courses you
know courses of future
activity
and you can evaluate them in terms of
your objective function
and then you can update them by means of
a recognition model
or by integrating prediction errors and
using predictive coding
then how do we build a formalism out of
just those
and the upside is that this does let us
look at the controls literature and say
all right
this is actually
optimal feedback stabilized control
we can look at some of the bounded
rationality literature
in cognitive science and Neuroscience
and say our objective function is a free
energy
that is
if you have to penalize how much you
change neural firing
over time
or how much you change your mind and
update your beliefs over time
because you only have so much metabolic
power in your head
then we include a penalty term for that
and we can say this can all just be done
by you know embodied simulation and
referent configuration motor control
does that mean this is how the brain
actually does things of course not
you know it does mean that if you want
to do your modeling with
I think
um Andy Clark tends to quote you know
Quine and say if you want to do if you
have a taste for Desert landscapes
then we've given you a computational
model
that is basically just sanded rocks
and as such yes it's something of a
hostile environment
you know walk without Rhythm you won't
detract the worm
in the planes of active
yeah if you want to live behind the
shield wall where we have
um
TD estimated value functions good for
you
in the stretched sigmoid with broad
variability so stretched that it is flat
and plain like but still highly
controllable within large bounds
that's where we're oscillating
yep
very interesting it'll be I think great
in our lab to pick up a few points from
am I the one cutting out again
I still see you yeah
it's okay yeah you're back all right you
flickered a bit okay
um in the last minutes we can
talk about some ideas from earlier in
the paper look at any of the figures and
then in the dot two that'll be awesome
to really approach the formalism and
help Dean on that ski Journey
um
what would be something to go to in
these last minutes
yes Dean and just and Eli maybe I'll be
able to get a chance to elaborate with
this bit more of Jordan in the next one
but I'm curious you you you took pains
and great at Great Lengths to say look
this doesn't map directly onto all the
complexities that we know exist but what
because you said to start at this in
2019 you had a bit of time on your hands
and then and then did kind of alluded
this at the beginning
were there discoveries that you made
that you didn't anticipate
because you you were very also very um
respectful in who you acknowledged as
sort of laying the the groundwork here
you had a bit of stability to work off
of but did you did you find yourself
introduced being introduced to things
that weren't there prior to you guys
coalescing around this and do you think
it continues to evolve or does it just
stay on a theoretical level
[Music]
um
so actually I'd say for me personally
the big unanticipated Discovery was just
how little we know
about interceptive neuroanatomy and
neurophysiology
and I mean in the periphery so
you know our lab with Lisa and Karen
Lisa handles the stuff above the neck
and so we've got you know Barrett and
Simmons 2015 there's a number of other
good papers saying essentially you look
at the brain architecture and it looks
like the at least in cortex
you know the interceptive and visceral
motor cortices are fairly Central to the
architecture and then you ask okay so
what kinds of signals are coming in from
the periphery
to then be subjected to predictive
processing
in cortex
and you basically get told well in
terreceptive signals obviously
so there was that moment when I was
working with Karen and realized oh okay
so
it looks like there's actually this
close analogy that we could hypothesize
between
the known function of a somatomotor
circuit
for voluntary motor control
and this way of handling Barrel reflex
function
and it looks like for the barrel reflex
you know you can voluntarily change the
gain or the tolerance those being
inverses of each other
changing the operating point you know
voluntarily doesn't seem to happen but
it does seem to shift
and it does begin to look as though ah
we can just we can stop just saying
you know there are interceptive signals
we don't know anything about them right
and instead ask how could we break down
the autonomic nervous system and the
interceptive periphery into these
you know control circuits where there's
a reference that flows from above
or is possibly built in as a prior and
then a sensor and then a motor neuron or
an effector
that again total
speculating one could imagine that Loop
could be ultra local
or even get cellular electrical
Junctions so as local as could be to
close the motor control Loop and then
there would be potentially a more meso
scale purely within the periphery
um maybe some sort of motor coordination
or vasoconstriction type actions that
are being enacted through local neural
networks and other systems and then when
you gotta make the call to the central
nervous system
and engage at that level
it's the highest capacity of like
Intermodal memory computation all these
other complex phenomena which then can
be seen to have their rightful place
maybe even in a specific brain region
but the entire integrated dodgeball
performance
is not going to be located to a brain
region any more than it would be located
to a fingertip
because it all needs to be coordinated
and not every call can be local
and not every call can be global so
finding out how bodies as territories
and our models as Maps
wire things up
is going to make models that are more
interpretable
better aligned with empirical data
making more useful predictions and
explanations
it's very interesting angle
and I would say just to piggyback a
little you know as a modeling Paradigm I
think this is one of the real strengths
of active inference
is that once you're dealing with these
probability densities and log
probability densities
you are
able to start sketching out these
hierarchical structures
and that doesn't mean that every
hierarchical active inference model is
automatically a map of the nervous
system but it does mean that you have a
language that is at least minimally
capable of expressing what we so
abundantly find in the empirical
evidence
yeah one part of the
paper that was very interesting what we
in reading it remarked how
although most papers are written in
words this one was very word forward
each section had a
preamble
content summary
sandwiching technique as did the paper
at a higher scale the nomenclature was
up front and clear and then the
relationship between the cumulative
distributions and the classical PDF type
probability densities
was made clear but this
exactly connects
something that has a um
in the generic case
a guaranteed inflection point
interpretable thresholded values this is
why sigmoid functions are used as
activation functions in artificial
neural networks
with
a uh optimizable laplacian approximation
like
inverted quadratic form
that is able to be used as a log
probability and so really like
especially with figure 9
showing the stepwise relationship
opens the door to like hey if you've
seen a sigmoid somewhere
now you can think about that as like a
PDF hiding a PDF bell curve
and then where you have seen a gaussian
or bell curve or a laplacian
approximation
you can go the other direction and think
about that in terms of a sigmoidal
response action
and so they're rarely connected so
clearly
though those with familiarity it's
almost the water that they swim in and
those without familiarity wouldn't see
the connection
and the The Challenge and the
opportunity is like to stick in the
middle
and stay
in the connection space
to raise attention to some of these
relationships which again otherwise you
could have a whole subfield of
physiology working on the sigmoid
response curve and a whole subfield of
hierarchical predictive processing
models working in the PDF space or log
PDF space
and it's just a derivative and a log or
an exponentiation and a derivation away
from those two Fields being formally
connected not just as like a speculative
review paper someone could or should do
this but like it's done we just didn't
know
tools so I think regarding the writing I
really have to have credit to Lisa and
Karen for a lot of things where
you know speaking of more speaking of
dialectical processes you know we have a
very simple writing dialectic on these
papers which is Junior author knows math
senior authors
did not specialize in math in their
undergrad or master's degree or key or
even PhD however good they are with it
now
and the result ends up being you know
you're always told to go back and
explain every single step and of course
Jordan you know who was here before was
helping a lot with the writing and the
structuring and the sign posting
and then
I think the ins the actual Insight that
you can take one of these sigmoids and
turn it into a PDF
I think came after
hammering our heads on some of the
embodied predictive processing
literature a bunch of times
foreign
it is one of those things that is
literally embodied
Dean
yeah I just wanted to get this in I I
What attracted me to the paper in the
first place was was that the Alice case
descending and the interception what
kept me going back to it was
um
and we talked about this in the dot zero
was
wayfinder that rule uh perfect
perspective swaps versus away
binder when I first started reading this
paper I I saw the metamorphosis from
identifying a way to find things and now
after having this conversation with you
today and and Jordan and of course the
usual suspects it it it's it's clearer
to me that this paper is trying to play
that role of being
wayfinder
perspective identifier as opposed to we
found the way or this is this is our way
to solve all the world's ills which it
of course I don't think it was ever your
intention but when you pull things that
are seemingly quite far apart like
allostasis and interception
I get excited but I I don't as you
pointed out pump the brake steam don't
get too excited here I mean we're doing
the best we can so on that level uh
my amygdala is still functioning
correctly
in our closing Thoughts with a driving
example
are we accumulating speed or minimizing
the amount of time or our speed limits
even set as exteriorized
right norms and stigmergic marks on the
niche
such that a variety of cars from a
sports car to a 18-wheeler can be within
a zone of optimal controllability taking
into account the presence of crosswalks
and so on and so alongside as we think
about what we want to explore in the dot
two alongside diving into formalisms
trying to do some
excavation and interception
on how and where
the economic optimization as
maximization
is implicitly used
and where some of these other Notions
that were being raised
without needing to be polemical or
replace value maximization
but where we can see
these other
survivability Criterion
as potentially different decompositions
of unified objective functions that are
informational and so on
I think that's going to be quite
far-ranging
because there's more situations I would
venture where we would rather have
controllability and expectation bounding
and meeting
rather than Point stacking
so final comments you like
yeah so I just really want to close by
re-emphasizing that
we don't you know we're not
I think I have this joke on my Twitter
profile abolish the value function and
that's really just a pun for the people
who can get it but you know we're not
trying to tell people contrary to their
subjective experience oh you don't
really have
you know value in your brain there's
actually just you know trying to track
your reference trajectory
so in the 0.2 we can talk about you know
which specific kinds of feedback control
what kinds of feedback mechanisms are
really being spoken of in this paper
and I think as
you know preview it's negative both
negative in the sense of avoiding
negative reinforcement and in the sense
of trying to flatten out a response
function and be able to proportionally
respond
so you know with the benefit of
hindsight
this paper is going to have a pretty
limited you know domain of application
but it's helpful in that it gives us a
language to turn around to the ex to the
empiricists and say this is what we want
to actually look for
any closing comments otherwise that's a
great note
well Eli and Jordan as well thanks for
coming out and for engaging in dot
Winery and we'll see you next week
thanks guys see you next week